自最后一个国王被赶出罗马城的四百年后
400 years after the last king was driven from the city,
罗马共和国统治着许多民族
the republic of Rome rules many nations,
但自己却内患重重
but cannot rule itself.
罗马城内，普通民众
The city is constantly roiled by conflict
和贵族之间纷争不断
between the common people and the nobility.
两位军人，两位老友
Power is shared and order maintained
分享着统治权，共同维持着国家的秩序
by two soldiers- old friends--
他们就是…格涅乌斯·庞贝·麦格纳斯和盖乌斯·优利乌斯·恺撒
Gnaeus Pompey Magnus and Gaius Julius Caesar.
曾经，庞贝被公认为更有王者风范
Once, Pompey was acknowledged by all to be the greater man,
在过去的八年里，庞贝一直维护着罗马的安定和平
but for the last eight years, while Pompey has kept the peace in Rome,
但与此同时，恺撒则发动了征服高卢的战争
Caesar has waged a war of conquest in Gaul
这场战争让他拥有了更多的财富和人心
that has made him ever more rich and popular.
权力的天平正渐倾斜
The balance of power is shifting,
贵族们也渐人心惶惶
and the nobility have grown fearful.
虽然出生贵族血统
Though of noble blood himself,
但恺撒却平易近人
Caesar stands with the common people.
一个这样的人…兵权在握，金钱在手
A man like that- an aristocrat with soldiers, money
又深受人民爱戴的贵族…或许就将成就帝王之业
and the love of the people- might make himself king.
波罗，入阵！
Pullo, formation!
波罗！
Pullo!
一字阵！
Single formation!
盾牌掩护！
Shields on me!
回到阵队里面去，你个酒鬼蠢货！
Get back in formation, you drunken fool.
整队！
Reform!
兵团士兵泰特斯·波罗，他是第13兵团的英雄
Legionary Titus Pullo is a hero of the 13th legion,
但看看他现在这个样子
but look at him now.
法律面前人人平等
Justice knows every man's number.
他犯下了严重的渎圣的罪行
He has committed a terrible sacrilege,
就将用他的性命来偿还！
and he will pay for it with his life!
这里的任何人犯了法，也都会象他这样
As will any man here who breaks the law.
斗殴者和醉酒者将被施以鞭刑
Brawlers and drunkards will be flogged.
盗窃者将被施以绞刑
Thieves will be strangled.
叛逃者将在十字架上被钉死
Deserters will be crucified.
这就完了？
Is that it?
我才刚开始享受呢
I was just beginning to enjoy myself.
在你面前是…
Before you...
凯而特人的儿子韦辛格托里克斯
vercingetorix, son of Celtil,
他是阿尔文尼部族的首领
chieftain of the tribe of the Arverni,
是依莱西亚要塞反抗者的总指挥
commander of the rebel stronghold of Elysia,
高卢人的君王
king of all the Gauls.
你要怎么处治他？
What would you have of him?
恺撒！
Caesar!
恺撒！恺撒！恺撒！
Caesar! Caesar! Caesar!
Hey!
嘿，外面发生了什么事？
Hey, what's going on?
嘿，我叫你呢！
Hey- here!
你个臭婊子养的
You piss-drinking sons of circus whores!
高卢人的首领向恺撒投降了
The chief of the Gauls has surrendered to Caesar.
战争结束了
The war is over.
别跟我说这个
Don't say that.
这些士兵们有两天的自由时间
The boys have been given two days liberty
洗劫城里的东西，据为己有
to sack the town and take personal spoils.
他们都发财了
They'll all be rich.
而我却被关在这里
And me in here!
过来，给我进去！
Come on, get in there!
400便士？你疯了吗？
400 denarii? Are you insane?
这只是底价
That's a floor price.
工匠，能生孩子的女人等等，这些我们还是会按老价钱付
We'll pay the usual premium for tradesmen and fertile women, et cetera.
庞贝·麦格纳斯的来信
From Pompey Magnus, sir.
把起价定在800便士左右吧
Set the floor closer to eight.
“我亲爱的朋友和伙伴，盖乌斯
"My dear friend and partner, Gaius,
我给你带来了一个可怕的消息”
I have terrible news."
原谅我
Forgive me.
我原谅你，我原谅你
I forgive you. I forgive you.
对我的奴隶好点  我会的
Be good to my slaves.  I will.
还有我的父亲
And to my father.
我会的
I will.
吻我
Kiss me.
你的头发
Your hair.
真有趣
Funny.
这些人不是东部穷苦的农民
This isn't miserable Eastern peasantry.
这些可是高卢国的贵族
This is the creme of the Gallic nations.
等市场上这样的货色多了你就卖不出去
A glut on the market. You won't be able to give them away.
700便士，不要讨价还价了  还送货到马赛去吗？
Seven, and be done with it.  On delivery to Masilia?
哦，你想得也太美了！  同意，你去负责细节
Oh, please!  Agreed. See to the details.
希望你把那些寄生虫卖了个好价钱
I hope you got a decent price off those parasites.
够不错了
Good enough.
有从罗马来的消息？
News from Rome?
庞贝写信来了
Pompey writes.
我女儿朱莉亚死于难产
My daughter Julia has died in childbirth.
我和你一起默哀
I grieve with you.
孩子呢？
The child?
是个女孩，保住了
Agirl--stillborn.
庞贝需要一位新夫人了
Pompey will be needing a new wife.
Caesar! Caesar! Caesar!
恺撒又运来了更多的从高卢得到的战利品
More of Caesar's spoils from Gaul.
恺撒！恺撒！
Caesar! Caesar!
老百姓高兴的时候搞出来的这些噪音是多可怕啊！
What a dreadful noise plebs make when they're happy.
这可是天籁之音
This is music.
等到恺撒煽动这些平民诛杀我们，他们嚎叫着要我喝我们的血的声音
Wait until Caesar starts them howling for our blood.
才会让你觉得真的可怕呢
Then you'll hear something dreadful.
凡是把女奴找回来的人
Afine reward isoffered
都将给予重金酬谢
for the return of a slavewoman,
不论这些女奴是被人从马略·多拉倍拉家偷走的还是自己潜逃的
stolen or absconded from the house of Marius Dolabella.
在庞贝·麦格纳斯和优利乌斯·恺撒的护卫下
Under the protection of Pompey Magnus
元老院明天会开会
and Julius Caesar, Senate sits tomorrow.
请大家注意了！
Be aware!
不允许有任何违反秩序的行为
No disorder will be tolerated.
好极了，泰门
That was lovely, Timon.
今天两匹种马被送到罗马来了
Two stallions have come to Rome today.
当然
Of course,
我太天真了
how childish of me.
你想要马  是的
You want the horse.  I do.
但你也别不高兴
But don't be sullen now.
我又没说和你做爱是件坏事
This was not a hardship for me.
我总是发觉象你这样的
I've always found something perversely erotic
好色小男人身上有些东西很诱人
about goaty little men.
别躲在那里，屋大维，进来
Do please don't lurk, Octavian. Come in.
别像个呆子一样，过来
Don't be a goose. Come in.
我买了一匹马
I've bought a horse.
是吗？
Have you?
据说是罗马最好的马
The best horse in Rome by all accounts.
我替你高兴
I'm very happy for you.
这是给你舅公的礼物
It's a gift for your great-uncle.
我想要你把它送到高卢去
I want you to take the animal to Gaul
亲自交给你舅公
and give it to him in person.
为什么？  因为等他回到罗马
Why?  Well, when he's back in Rome,
每个人都会争着给他送礼，所以我们必须作第一个
everyone will be giving him gifts. We must be first.
我想他短时间内不会回罗马的
I doubt he will return to Rome anytime soon.
元老院对他颇有敌意
The Senate's hostility will prevent him.
从法律上说，这不是…  哦，别跟我说什么法律
Legally speaking, it is not-  Please don't start speaking legally.
你知道我有多烦它  去高卢，路很远啊
You know how it bores me.  It's a long way to Gaul.
正是，你不过是个小男孩
Exactly. While yet a mere boy,
可你敢于冒着生命危险去给你敬爱的舅公献礼
you would risk your life to honor your beloved great-uncle.
你能独自一人骑着那高贵的白马去到恺撒的营地
You ride into Caesar's camp alone, on a noble white stallion.
这样的礼物，他可不会轻易忘记
That's a gift he won't soon forget.
独自一人？  是啊，会有很多奴隶跟着你
Alone?  Well, you'll have plenty of slaves.
你会很安全的
You'll be perfectly safe.
而且你也会让你的妈妈十分骄傲和开心
And you'll make your mamma very proud and happy.
卡托，元老院听你发言
Cato, the Senate hears you.
庞贝·麦格纳斯…
Pompey Magnus...
我有个问题关于你的朋友，你的共同执政官…
I have a question concerning your friend and co-consul--
维纳斯的爱人盖乌斯·优利乌斯·恺撒
the darling of venus, Gaius Julius Caesar.
他的座位为什么仍然是空着的？
Why does his chair remain empty?
他为什么还不返回罗马来？他的非法战争已经结束了
Why does he not come home? His illegal war is over.
高卢人早就下跪投降了
Gaul is long since on it's knees.
恺撒为什么还不让他英勇的将士们
Why does Caesar keep his brave soldiers
与他们的家人和朋友团聚
from their families and friends?
在长达八年的时间里
For eight long years,
他就像一匹狼一样
he has gorged himself like a wolf
饱食着高卢人的血肉
on the blood of Gaul,
也由此变得富可敌国
and thereby made himself monstrously rich.
为什么？  坐下！
Why?  Sit down!
为什么他出钱给那些暴民搞比赛和角斗，还给他们开筵席？
Why does he ply the mob with races and fights and gaudy feasts?
为什么他帮这个元老院里的
Why has he paid the debts
每个无耻之徒偿还他们的债务？
of every reprobate fool in this Senate house?
为什么？
Why?!
让我来告诉你们为什么他做这些事情
I'll tell you why he does these things.
是想给他自己买皇冠
He wants to buy himself a crown.
他想破坏共和
He wants to destroy the Republic
然后统治罗马，作个血腥独裁者！
and rule Rome as a bloody tyrant!
这就是原因！
That's why!
因此，我提议…
Therefore, I move...
立即终止恺撒在高卢的行政权
that Caesar's governorship in Gaul be terminated immediately,
解散他的军队
that his armies be disbanded
召他回罗马来等候制裁
and that he be recalled to Rome to answer charges
要指控他发动非法战争
of illegal warfare,
偷窃，行贿，和叛国罪！
theft, bribery and treason!
很精彩，卡托
very good, Cato.
你还是一如既往充满活力和热情啊
Full of vim and verve, as usual.
恺撒…
Caesar...
对广大民众一直非常慷慨
has been generous to the people
因为他像我一样热爱这些人民
because he loves the people as I do.
这个国家是由人民自己当家作主的，而不是你们这些高级的贵族
It is the people that rule, not you fine nobleman.
是庞贝的军队在作主
It is Pompey's soldiers that rule,
不是我们这些高级的贵族
not we fine nobleman.
我来为大家节省点时间，不用再无谓地争吵
I'm going to save us all hours of useless clamor
我用我的执政官否决权，否决你的提议
and use my consular veto on your motion.
好  我不…
Yes!  I do not--
我不…  静一静！
I do not-  Silence!
我们不是小孩，让执政官把话说完
Are we children? Let the consul speak.
谢谢你，西赛罗
Thank you, Cicero.
我不…  可是…
I do not-  However...
在你继续之前请允许我先说两句
if I might say a few words before you continue.
当你面对一只饿狼的时候
When confronted by a hungry wolf,
去刺激这头野兽是很不明智的
it is unwise to goad the beast,
如果照卡托说的做，就是去刺激它
as Cato would have us do.
但是同样不明智的
But it is equally unwise
是把这只咆哮的野兽看成
to imagine the snarling animal
是朋友而伸出援手
a friend and offer your hand
就好像庞贝这样
as Pompey does.
那你是不是要建议我们爬到树上去啊
Perhaps you would have us climb a tree.
恺撒是我发圣誓结义的兄弟
Caesar is my brother by sacred oath.
我清楚他的心意，他是我的朋友
I know his heart. He is my friend
也是共和国忠实的儿子
and a faithful son of the Republic.
除非有人有证据说他不是
And until anyone proves that he is not,
否则我永远不会背叛他
I will never betray him.
庞贝·麦格纳斯，我亲爱的朋友，见到你真高兴
Pompey Magnus, my dear fellow, you're well met.
西比乌，卡托
Scipio, Cato.
我想你们不是笑剧的爱好者吧
I would not take you for lovers of the mime.
介绍我女儿给你认识，科妮莉娅
You know my daughter, Cornelia.
贵族普布利乌斯的遗孀，他战死在卡雷了
Widow of noble Publius who died at Carrhae.
科妮莉娅，你丈夫是个杰出的罗马战士
Cornelia, your husband was a fine Roman.
谢谢你
I thank you.
父亲，我不应该在这样的场合出现
Father, my presence is not appropriate.
舞台上有个淫荡的女人
There's a lewd woman on the stage.
我没注意
I had no notion.
那我们就不久留了
We will not linger then.
庞贝，祝你有个愉快的夜晚
Pompey, a pleasant good night.
如果你不介意，我们可以单独谈谈吗？
If it please you, might we speak alone?
仅仅是靠贵族们
Neither we aristocrats alone
或光靠你和你的将士们都不可能打败恺撒
nor you and your soldiers alone can crush Caesar.
别说了
Stop there.
我没说你想搞垮恺撒
I do not say that you wish to crush Caesar,
我就是说，如果你真想的话，你自己一个人干不来
I only say that if you did wish it, you could not do it alone.
我不需要你的贵族
I have no need of you noble gentleman.
只要我一跺脚
I have only to stamp my feet
我的军团就会崛起，遍布于整个意大利
and legions will spring up all over ltaly!
把恺撒像只虫子一样地辗死
I can squash Caesar like an insect
只要我想这样做
if I wished it so.
可是我不想这样
I do not wish it.
和他断绝关系，庞贝！
Renounce him, Pompey!
罢免恺撒！
Renounce Caesar!
和我们结盟，他的兵力自然就会减弱了
Ally yourself with us and his strength will wither away.
你才是真正的掌权者
It is you who is the real power.
你才是人民真正爱戴的人
It is you the people truly love.
你以为当恺撒没有了
Think you they will still shout Caesar's name
高卢的小玩意扔给街上的人的时候，他们还会高呼他的名字吗？
when he runs out of Gallic trinkets to throw to them?
你以为我会在意街上的人叫谁的名字吗？
Think you I care what names are shouted in the streets?
没有比这个更重要的了
Nothing is more important.
你要我公然背叛朋友
You ask me to openly betray a friend.
这个我做不到
I cannot do it.
晚安
Good night.
噢，我的小傻弟弟
Oh, silly baby brother.
不会有事的
Everything will be all right.
他很完美对不对？体面的小战士
Is he not perfect? Proper little soldier.
他很害怕  胡说
He's scared.  Nonsense.
罗马男人从来不害怕
Roman men are never scared.
他就是有点舍不得离开妈妈
He's just sad to be leaving his mamma.
你不是害怕了吧，屋大维？
You're not scared, are you, Octavian?
你当然不会，很快就到了
Of course you're not. Time flies.
亲爱的，给我一个吻
Give me a kiss, my love.
安德鲁斯…
Andros...
给我把他安全地带回来，不让我就把你小孩的眼珠
bring him back safe or I'll use the eyes
挖出来当珠子串
of your children for beads.
莱科，那匹马…不是很贵吧，我希望
Lyco, the horse- not too expensive I hope.
对不起，先生，那匹马已经卖掉了
I'm sorry, sir, the horse was sold already.
卖给优利亚家的阿提娅了  阿提娅？
To Atia of the Julii.  Atia?
她把马送到高卢去了…
She's sending it to Gaul--
作为给恺撒的礼物
a gift for Caesar.
他真该死！
Damn him!
他非要什么都抢去吗？
Must he have everything?
反正也要派你到高卢去
As you were going to be in Gaul anyway,
我不如一石二鸟
I might kill two birds with one stone.
让我看看你
Let me look at you.
还是那么丑，我怕你要这么说吧
As ugly as ever, I'm afraid.
一点也不，你成熟多了，布鲁图斯
Not at all. Age suits you, Brutus.
我们有多久没见了
How long has it been?
五年？  不，六年
Five years?  No, six.
哈，真有创意啊
Oh, how clever.
这简直就是个像样的房子嘛
It's almost like a proper house.
Oh...
我为你的所失深表遗憾
I deeply regret your loss.
朱莉娅的事情，太可惜了
Julia and so forth. Horrible business.
向你哀悼，真的
Condolences, really.
跟我说说，你妈妈怎么样了？
Now tell me, how's your mother?
和从前一样
The same as ever.
她要我向你问好，还要我问你
She sends her love, demands to know
为什么你几个月都没给她写信了
why you haven't written to her in months.
只要你作我的信使，我补救还来得及吧
I can remedy that if you'll be my courier.
我有好几封信要你帮我送
I have several letters to send.
只要我有力气坐到马背上去
If I can ever bring myself to get on another horse.
来这之前，我不知道高卢居然有这么远
I had no conception that Gaul was so far away.
布鲁图斯，我的老伙计…
Brutus, me old cock...
你到这儿干什么来了？
what on earth are you doing here?
马克·安东尼，你好啊
Mark Antony, how nice.
我到纳贝看我的堂兄来了
I've been visiting my cousin in Narbo.
哦？你那个傻子堂兄怎么样了？
Oh? How is that idiot cousin of yours?
他…  事实上，对不起，我有点急事
He was-  Actually, I'm in a bit of a rush.
我需要，大概半塔兰特的黄金
I need, say, a half talent of gold.
是吗？  让你看看他有多信任我
Do you?  See how he trusts me.
是为鹰旗要的  当然，斯特雷波
For the eagle.  Of course. Strabo!
给马克·安东尼大人半塔兰特的黄金
Give his honor Mark Antony a half talent of gold.
半塔兰特的黄金？  一分也不要多给
A half talent of gold.  And not a penny more.
上帝啊
Dominus.
我不知道你怎么能容忍那个人
I don't know how you tolerate that man.
他就是喜欢斗嘴
He likes to fight.
他的举止行为，让人觉得他一点家教都没有
The way he carries on, one might think he came from no family at all.
他是有点粗俗的一面，不过我不介意
He does have a vulgarian streak. I don't mind it.
那个鹰旗是怎么回事？
What is this about the eagle?
是我的军队标志被强盗偷去了
My personal standard was stolen by brigands.
很麻烦
Abad business.
军团士兵已经很想家，士气很低沉了
The legions were already homesick and surly when the eagle was taken,
加上鹰旗再被偷走，他们肯定要造反了
now they're positively mutinous.
他们认为这是我厄运的征兆
The men think it's a sure sign of my doom,
就像一群鹅一样叫嚷着要解散军队
and they're clamoring like geese for disbandment.
他们看起来倒不像不高兴的样子
They did not seem so unhappy.
他们从来不会表现出不满，不然是会挨鞭子的
Well, they never flaunt their discontent. Gets them whipped.
我告诉你，布鲁图斯
I tell you, Brutus,
我已经没有办法了
I'm at my wits end.
屋大维少爷…
Master Octavian...
离瓦西欧只有几里路了
vasio is only a few more miles.
没有我的允许，不许碰我
Do not touch me without permission.
给我水
Water.
卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯
Lucius Vorenus.
你是个聪明人
You have a brain.
那些护民官是这么说的
So the tribunes say.
那么告诉我，如果要你去把恺撒的鹰旗找回来
So tell me, if it were you who had to retrieve Caesar's eagle,
你打算怎么做？
how would you go about it?
我会把从高卢各个部落抓来的俘虏
Uh, I'd take captives from every tribe in Gaul
一个一个地钉在十字架上
and crucify them one by one
直到有人说出鹰旗的下落为止
until someone tells me where the eagle is.
然后，我就会火速地悄悄派一到两个人
Then, I would go in quick and quiet with one or two men
然后…去把它偷回来
and... steal it back.
好，我们想到一起去了
Good. We are of one mind.
照做  照做，长官？
Do it.  Do it, sir?
我记得第三军团有个分队专门负责拷问俘虏
Well, I believe there's a torture detachment with the third,
但你也可以选自己的人去做，只要你愿意
but you may choose your own men if you wish.
这里是四分之一塔兰特的黄金，给你作行贿之类的事情用
There's a quarter talent there, for bribes and such.
好好利用  是，长官
Spend it wisely.  Sir.
不！请把我放下来！
No! Please let me down!
让我下来！
Let me down!
放我下来，我知道…我知道鹰旗的下落
Let me down! I know- I know where the eagle is.
说  是那些蓝色的西班牙人偷去的
Speak.  The Blue Spaniards,
他们来呆了一晚上…
they came to stay for one night...
然后就骑马朝卡达西去了
and then rode to the Cadurci lands.
求求你！求求你！放我下来！
Please! Please please. Let me down.
卡达西
Cadurci.
我真是倒霉透了
Fortune pisses on me.
请让我下来！  放他们下来
Please let me down!  Take them down.
门神，佛克琉斯
Forculus,
如果你在天有灵的话
if you be the right god for the business here,
我乞求你帮助我
I call on you to help me.
如果你能打开这扇门
If you will open this door,
我就杀一头白色的羊羔祭奉你
then I will kill for you a fine white lamb,
或者，要是我买不到便宜的羊
or, failing that, if I couldn't get a good one at a decent price,
我就杀六只乳鸽给你
then six pigeons.
门神佛克琉斯，我向你发誓
This, Forculus, I vow to you.
兵团士兵泰特斯·波罗，起立
Legionary Titus Pullo, stand up.
他来这干什么？
What's he doing here?  You are to be released
你被释放了
to the command of Second Spear Centurion Lucius vorenus.
这是第二箭枪队百夫长卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯的旨意
按照他说的去做，只要你让他满意，就可以饶你不用去角斗场上被人打死
Do your duty to his satisfaction, and you'll be spared damnation in the arena.
我连站在这个臭狗屎矮子旁边都不乐意，更别说帮他做事了
I won't even stand next to this short-assed shit,
我还是呆在这吧，谢谢你了
Ieave alone serve under him. I'll stay here, thanks very much.
这命令是直接来自于马克·安东尼阁下的
These orders come direct from his Excellency Mark Antony himself.
要你去找回恺撒的鹰旗
You are to retrieve Caesar's eagle.
要我，去找回恺撒的鹰旗？
Me, retrieve Caesar's eagle?
布鲁图斯  妈妈！
Brutus?  Mamma!
你不知道回到家的感觉有多好
You can't imagine how good it is to be home.
你晒得跟豆子一样黑了
You're as brown as a bean.
不过这让我看起来英气风发
It makes me look quite soldierly though.
是啊，是啊
It does, it does.
你堂兄马赛琉斯好不好？  他很枯燥乏味，不过身体还不错
How is cousin Marcellus?  Tedious but healthy.
恺撒呢？  谁？
And Caesar?  Who?
别跟我兜圈子
Don't be cruel.
他还好吗？他问起我了吗？
Is he well? Did he ask of me?
他有吗？我记不起来了
Did he? I can't recall.
我想是没有
I think not.
不过他倒的确写了封信给你
He did write you a letter though.
哦，你这个坏家伙
Oh, you beast.
“最亲爱的赛维莉娅，原谅我长时间没有给你写信
"Dearest Servilia, forgive my long silence.
最近的这几个月里全是血雨腥风，金戈铁马
These last long months were all blood and iron and mud,
没有时间给朋友写信
and no time for letters to friends.
但我的确一直在想念着你，带着深深的情意
Be sure that I have been thinking of you with great affection.
我渴望和你在一起和你独处”
I long to be together and alone with you."
“深深的情意”
"Great affection."
渴望和你独处
Longs to be alone with you.
你认为他跟他的妻子也这么说吗？
You think he says such things to his wife?
“情意”？是什么？
"Affection"? What's that?
他不可能说“爱”
He could not say "love."
你难道还想让他为你弹竖琴吗？
Would you have him pluck a harp?
他是个军人，不是诗人
He's a soldier, not a poet.
天色渐晚了
The day dwindles.
我们的客人要到了
Our guests will be arriving.
你马骑地不错啊，几乎和我差不多好了
You ride well, almost as well as me.
波罗，注意你对我的称呼
Pullo, you will address me correctly.
几乎和我差不多好了，长官
Almost as well as me, sir.
我是天生的，我猜我父亲大概是个努比亚人
Me, I'm a natural. My father was a Ubian probably.
你从哪儿学的骑术，这么好？
Where did you learn to ride so nice?
你爱说不说吧，我只不过是想气氛融洽点
Please yourself. Only trying to be pleasant.
我母亲家那边的人在穆提那养马
My mother's people raised horses in Mutina.
穆提那，靠近瑞吉姆？在它北边附近？
Mutina, near Reggium? Up round there?
在北边  好地方
Up there.  Good country.
听着，长官，谢谢你带我来干这个差事
Listen, sir, thank you, for taking me on this job.
这是个很大度道歉的办法  道什么歉？
A noble way to make amends.  Amends?
我被关进监狱是拜你所赐啊
For getting me into this cac by calling me names.
不客气  不，我不会忘记的
Think nothing of it.  Never. I won't forget.
泰图斯·波罗从不忘恩
Titus Pullo never forgets a favor.
哈！  你“哈”是什么意思？
Hah!  What you mean, "Hah"?
你觉得我们找到鹰旗的机会有多大？
What do you think our chances are of finding the eagle?
13军从不辱命，不是吗？
13th never fails, eh?
几乎没有机会，鹰旗可能在任何地方
Little or no chance. The eagle might be anywhere.
被焚烧了，熔化了或者是被沉到海底了
Buried, melted down, sunk to bottom of the sea.
我们等于是在黑夜里追踪一只黑狗
We are hunting a black dog in the night.
然而找不到鹰旗和把鹰旗搞丢了差不多是同罪的
And not finding the eagle is much the same as losing it.
我们会颜面尽失的，所以，我选择你
We will be disgraced. Now, I chose you
你因为你已经够丢脸了，而且你有死罪在身
because you are disgraced already and condemned to die.
那么是说你根本就不是在赔礼道歉喽？
So you weren't making amends at all, then?
波罗，事实上你已经是死路一条了
Pullo, in effect, you're dead already.
死一个酒鬼蠢货对军团来说根本不算是损失
The loss of one drunken fool does little damage to the legion.
如果我已经死路一条了，长官
If I'm dead already then, sir,
你得要注意跟我说话的语气
you should take care how you speak to me.
如果我已经一无所有了
If I've got nothing to lose,
那又有什么能阻止我把你剁成肉酱
what's to stop me cutting you into little gobs
然后骑马而去的呢？
and riding off, eh?
有什么能阻止我的，长官？
What's to stop me, sir?
要是作为一个第13军团的战士的荣誉感还不足以阻止你的话
Well, if your honor as a soldier of the 1 3th isn't enough,
那么我就要靠自己高超的博斗技巧了
then I'll have to rely on my superior fighting skills.
高超的博斗技巧？  嗯
Superior fighting skills?  Mmm.
很好
very good.
当然，你们还要想象一下，这么长的头发
And of course, you have to imagine long hair down to here,
浓密的胡须，最让人恶心的臭味
huge moustaches, the most horrific stench.
他们只吃生肉，而且从不洗澡
They eat only raw meat and never wash.
哦，他们的确有个令人钦佩的风俗
Oh, they do have one admirable custom.
他们解决政治争端的方法
They settle their political disputes
是靠一场生死格斗
by single combat to the death.
绝妙的办法  不是吗？
Excellent idea.  lsn't it?
妈妈总是唠叨要我参与政治
Mother is always nagging me to attend politics.
这是我们家族的传统
Well, it's been our family's tradition
还有责任…
and duty for...
五百年了
500 years.
都是些枯燥的可怕的东西
It is such dreadfully dull stuff.
你看，如果我们的元老院也按日耳曼风格来办事
Now you see, if our Senate conducted business in the German style,
那我就肯定会去看的
I should certainly go and watch.
是啊，没有冗长的诉讼和无止境的争辩
Yeah, no tedious lawsuits and endless debates,
只有剑和匕首…
just swords, daggers--
那就有趣多了  布鲁图斯，过来说句话
much more entertaining.  Brutus, a word.
告诉我，你是个好裁判
Tell me, you are a good judge.
我亲爱的朋友恺撒如何？
How is my dear friend Caesar?
呃，他…
Well, he is--
他还不错，我觉得
he's been better, I think.
很…很疲倦，老实说
very- very weary, to be honest.
有点意志消沉  恺撒，意志消沉？
A little demoralized.  Caesar demoralized?
绝不会  他的军旗被偷了
Never.  His standard was stolen.
他怎么会让这样的蠢事发生？
How did he let a foolish thing like that happen?
我不知道，但他对这件事的态度还有这件事引起来的骚动…
I don't know, but his manner and uproar about it--
你知道那些庶民们对这样的事会有什么样的反应…
you know how plebeians can be about such things--
不顾一切地想回家，都很想造反了
desperate to come home, mutinous.
我听说了那里有些不满情绪
I have heard there was some discontent,
但造反？难以置信
but mutinous? Hard to believe.
你可以想象嘛
Can you imagine?
毕竟，他这样对他的将士
After all he has done for them,
他也不敢肯定他们会不会…
he is not sure whether they will--
再继续替他卖命打仗了
will fight for him anymore.
而且这些下等阶层的人也没有什么所谓忠心耿耿的意识
And the lower classes have a very very crude sense of loyalty.
我无冒犯之意  啊？
No offense.  Eh?
我不是说你，你也是来自下层社会的人
I don't mean you. You are lower class,
不过，我是说下等阶层的人，一般而言
but that is to say, the lower class in general, however.
都没有什么忠心的意识
A very crude sense of loyalty.
失陪一下
Excuse me.
“我亲爱的侄女
"My dear niece,
我希望你和孩子们都过地好
I hope you and the children are well.
我有个任务给你
I have a task for you.
政策上我应该给庞贝找位新夫人
Policy dictates I give a new wife to Pompey,
但我走了太久，所以不知道
but I have been gone too long to know who among the females
我们家族里的女性，哪个合适
of our family would be suitable.
我可以去问卡尔普蕊娜，尽管她是个出色的妻子
I would ask Calpurnia, but though an excellent wife,
可是办这样的事，她却没什么眼力
she has no eye for this kind of business.
帮我个忙，挑选任何一个
Do me the favor of selecting whichever girl
只要是你认为最能取悦庞贝的人
you think most likely to please
然后以我的名义把她送给他”
and offer her to him in my name."
哦，对不起，我想事情想得出神了
Excuse me, I was far away.
我希望，恺撒没带给你什么坏消息吧
Caesar has no bad news for you, I hope.
不，一点也没有，一点也没有
No, not at all. Not at all.
多美好的宴会啊  谢谢你
What a lovely party.  Thank you.
还是不及你穿着这条裙子那么美好
Not as lovely as you look in that dress.
嘘
Shh.
还有奥克塔维娅…真漂亮
And Octavia- beautiful.
这是我的努力的结果
Well, I try.
她自己总是很懒散，不修边幅的
She will insist on slouching.
屋大维呢？
Where's Octavian?
他去高卢了
He's in Gaul.  Oh.
圣母说你的儿子不会有危险的
Great Mother says no harm shall come to your boy.
那就好
Good.
跟我说说，你的婚姻如何？
Tell me now, how goes your marriage?
格雷毕斯是个好男人
Glabius is a good man.
你这么说我很惊讶，我一直以为你们俩之间有问题呢
You surprise me. I always thought there were difficulties between you.
你一定总要这样一针见血吗？
Must you always have a needle in hand?
我只不过是问问，原谅我的好奇
I was only asking. Excuse my curiosity.
过去是有些困难
There was some difficulties in the past,
但是我们已经克服了
but we overcame them.
我们很相爱
We love each other very much.
哦，真遗憾，现在我觉得不安了
Well, that's a shame. Now I feel bad.
我原以为你会很高兴的
I thought you'd be overjoyed.
你什么意思？
What do you mean?
舅公优利乌斯打算把你嫁给
Uncle Julius intends to marry you
庞贝·麦格纳斯
to Pompey Magnus.
舅公优利乌斯打算…  我知道庞贝的品位是有点低
Uncle Julius intends-  Pompey is a touch low in manner,
但我听人说，他是个完美无缺的爱人
but I'm told he's a perfectly adequate lover.
而且你就是罗马的第一夫人了
And you shall be the first woman in Rome.
明摆着，我们得让你和格雷毕斯离婚
We shall have to get you divorced from Glabius, obviously.
越快越好
Quick as poss.
我不会这么做的
I will not do it. I love my husband.
我爱我的丈夫
If you do not divorce Glabius willingly,
如果你不心甘情愿地和格雷毕斯离婚
那么恺撒就会要格雷毕斯和你离婚
then Caesar will ask Glabius to divorce you.
格雷毕斯会拒绝的  当然，但他就会被杀死
And Glabius will refuse.  Doubtless, and then he'll be killed.
有人会愿意这样的事发生吗？
And does anybody want that to happen?
恺撒不会这么做的
Caesar would not do that.
那个男人在高卢呆了八年了
The man's been in Gaul for eight years.
他就是一头凶残的野兽
He's practically a wild beast.
那个男人眼中含着泪
The man has tears in his eyes.
眼泪
Tears.
他爱我
He loves me.
一个娘娘腔的丈夫有什么用
A womanish husband is no use to anyone.
还有你的那些仆人！有什么好大惊小怪的！
And your servants! What a fuss!
我看你把他们喂的太好了
I think you feed them too much.
我看再多上点砒霜，盖娅
A little more arsenic, I think, Gaia.
高兴点，奥克塔维娅
Try to look a little more cheerful, Octavia.
这是为了我们家庭的利益  我不在乎
It's for the good of the family.  I don't care.
你和我，还有你弟弟在这个世界上相依为命
You and I and your brother are alone in the world.
我们要坚强  不是只有我们三个
We have to be strong.  We are not alone.
恺撒是…  恺撒在高卢
Caesar is-  Caesar is in Gaul.
庞贝在这里
Pompey is here.
勇敢点，我亲爱的
Courage, my love.
帕提亚人威胁着我的左侧
The Parthian were threatening my left flank.
如此一来，我并没有按照惯例
And so, rather than shorten the line
缩短战线
as would be conventional,
而是把我的后备骑兵送到翼侧反而包围了在我左侧的部队
I sent in my cavalry reserve and outflanked the flankers.
好极了，麦格纳斯，真精彩
Bravo, Magnus. Masterly.
他是不是很棒，奥克塔维娅？
Is he not, Octavia, masterly?
很棒
Masterly.
麦格纳斯，告诉我，说实话
Magnus, tell me something, and be honest.
你喜欢我的女儿吗？
Does my daughter please you?
非常喜欢，毋须置疑
very pleasing, no doubt.
那么我告诉你，恺撒
Then I can tell you that Caesar,
作为他对你长久友谊的象征
as a token of his abiding friendship,
愿意把她送给你作妻子
would like to offer her to you in marriage.
Ah.Ahem.
她不是嫁给年轻的格雷毕斯了吗？
She is not married to young Glabius?
离婚了
Divorced.
也许你需要时间考虑  不好意思
Perhaps you need time to think.  Excuse me,
我没有心理准备
I was taken unawares.
我怎能拒绝这样一个可敬又高贵的新娘呢？
How could I refuse such a worthy and dignified bride?
恺撒太慷慨了  太好了
Caesar is far too generous.  Excellent.
我们要等到下个月
We would have to wait until next month
再办一个正式的仪式
for an actual ceremony, of course,
是要等朱莉娅的丧期过了以后
when Julia's mourning days are over.
当然，当然，不过你可以
Of course, of course. But you may take
在任何时候履行丈夫的权利
your betrothal privileges any time you wish.
要是你愿意，现在就可以
Now, if you like.
这个就真的不需要了  别傻了
Really, that's not necessary.  Don't be silly.
奥克塔维娅会乐意的
Octavia would love to.
不用不好意思
There's no need for shyness.
毕竟，我们现在都是一家人了
We're all family now, after all.
英国女人…都是些野蛮的婊子
British women- now, that's savage cunny.
你得像猎鹿一样对她们穷追不舍
You have to hunt them down like deer.
记住，一旦你把她们搞到手了
Mind, once you get them under you,
想怎么马虎她们都行
slack as your best Narbo scortum.
除了女人你就不能想点别的？
Do you care for nothing but women?
还有什么？哦，还有吃的？
What else is there? Food, I suppose.
你不喜欢女人？
You don't like women?
我当然喜欢
Of course I do.
我结婚了
I'm married to one.
我妻子叫内奥比  我明白了，百夫长可以结婚？
I have a wife, Niobe.  I see. Centurions can marry then?
我有特许
I received a special dispensation.
特许？那她肯定是个什么不赖的…
A special dispensation? She must be some good...
女人
woman.
她是
She is.
你有很长时间没见她了吧
Been awhile since you've seen her then.
7年零140天
Seven years, 140 days.
挺不容易的，祝你好运
That's hard. May fortune smile on you.
我，我的要求很简单
Me, I have simpler tastes.
我就想杀死我的敌人拿走他们的黄金
I like to kill my enemy, take their gold
享受他们的女人
and enjoy their women.
就这么简单，为什么要在吊在一棵树上呢？
That's it. Why tie yourself to one?
那还有什么滋味？有什么乐子？
Where's the flavor? Where's the joy?
你最近一次和女人睡完觉后
When was the last time you had a woman
他们没有哭着嚷着找你要钱，是在什么时候？
who wasn't crying or wanting payment?
你站第一班岗，等月亮当顶的时候叫醒我
You're on first watch. Wake me when the moon's at the zenith.
遵命，长官
Right you are, sir.
站住！
Halt!
见他妈的鬼！
Sons of Dis!
反正那些也不是什么好马
They weren't such good horses anyway.
我手下的士兵曾在扎马和麦格尼西亚作战
My people fought at Zama and Magnesia,
我的父亲曾和苏拉同骑，而我却落到这样的境地…
my father rode with Sulla, and I'm reduced to this--
没有马骑，还被几个小鬼给抢了
unhorsed and robbed by children.
好漂亮的马
Nice horse.
看过来，战神，看过来，战神
Look here, Mars. Look here, Mars.
我是泰图斯·波罗，这些血淋淋的人是我给您的礼物
I am Titus Pullo. These bloody men, my gift to you.
感谢上帝你的出现，我非常感激你
Thank the gods you came. I am extremely grateful to you.
Aye!
听着，我命令你马上给我松绑
Listen to me. I order you to release me this instant.
一个奴隶还敢这样说话啊，凭你这张嘴，你休想活得长
Fine way for a slave to talk. You won't get far with a mouth on you.
我不是奴隶，我是优利亚家的盖乌斯·屋大维
I'm no slave. I'm Gaius Octavian of the Julii.
优利乌斯·恺撒的孙外甥  盖乌斯什么？
Great-nephew of Julius Caesar.  Gaius who?
我是罗马贵族公民
I am a Roman citizen of noble birth,
我命令你割断这些绳子
and I order you to cut these ropes.
说“请”
Say please.
请你
Please.
我保证你们会得到丰厚的酬谢
Be assured you will be amply rewarded
作为你们为我效劳的奖赏
for your services to me.
看到他多会说话啊
See how good he talks?
他说的挺像真的，我相信他
He's convincing, I'll give him that.
恺撒会证明我是谁的，带我去见他
Caesar will prove who I am. Take me to him.
现在还不行
We cannot do that as yet.
我们有命令在身  什么命令？
We have orders.  What orders?
我们要找回恺撒被盗走的鹰旗
We are to retrieve Caesar's stolen eagle.
恺撒才不会在意他的鹰旗呢
Caesar wouldn't pull a hair for his eagle.
你们干的这是个徒劳的差事
You're on a fool's errand.
如果恺撒不在意鹰旗，那他为什么派我们去找？
If Caesar doesn't care about the eagle, why did he send us to find it?
如果不花一点气力去找，那他就看起来太奇怪了
It would look strange if he made no efforts.
实际上，鹰旗不见了对恺撒是有好处的
Actually, losing the eagle is useful to Caesar.
为什么这对恺撒有好处？
Why would that be useful to Caesar?
因为庞贝不是个深奥的哲人
Because Pompey is no deep philosopher.
他会把这个象征性的损失当作是真实的弱像
He will take a symbolic loss for a real weakness.
解释给我听
Explain.
恺撒不想首先出击对付自己的老友
Caesar doesn't want to strike the first blow against an old friend,
所以他想引诱庞贝先来攻击他
so he wishes to lure Pompey into attacking him first.
而只有让庞贝相信恺撒变弱了他才会这么做
Pompey will only do this if he believes Caesar is weak.
不，他们两个好得像亲兄弟一样
No. They're as good as brothers, those two.
朱莉娅死了之后，他们俩之间最后一条真实的纽带就断了
When Julia died, the last true bond between them was cut.
恺撒把普通大众的爱戴都从庞贝那里赢了过去
Caesar has taken the love of the common people from Pompey,
这就是他最有价值的财富，战争是不可避免的了
and that was his most prized possession. A battle is inevitable.
波罗！
Pullo.
蓝色的西班牙人！
Blue Spaniards!
早上好，舅公
Good morning, Uncle!
屋大维？
Octavian?
这是庞贝的人，我错看了他
One of Pompey's men. I misjudged him.
我原以为还要些计谋才能让他反我
I thought it would take strategy to turn him against me,
他肯定是在朱莉娅死的时候就决心与我为敌了
but he must have turned the moment Julia died.
亏他这段时间还在元老院维护你
And all the while he was defending you in the Senate.
他滑的像条沙丁鱼，可怜的傻瓜
He has the cunning of a sardine, poor fool.
斗争开始了
The battle begins.
是时候了
Abouttime.
是波卡·朱诺
Porca Juno.
“最亲爱的庞贝
"Dearest Pompey,
我想这个是你的人
I believe the enclosed man belongs to you.
事先告诉你，我已决定
A quick note to tell you I have decided to winter
带13军团驻扎到靠近家乡的拉文纳过冬
the 13th Legion closer to home, at Ravenna,
所以很快我就能当面问候你了”
so I shall soon have the pleasure of paying you homage in person."
庞贝！庞贝！
各位，这是我的新夫人，科妮莉亚
All of you, this is my new wife, Cornelia.
如果你能施展一点魅力
Maybe if you'd summoned a little charm
而不是像头迟钝的老母牛一样老苦着一张脸
instead of moping about like some torpid old she-cow,
这种事就不会发生  哦，我的天哪！
this would never have happened.  Oh, my dear!
别这样，我只是在说气话
Please, I was only speaking in anger.
每个人都知道你被拒绝是出于政治上的原因
Everyone knows it's a political repudiation on account
庞贝和恺撒现在是敌人了
Pompey and Caesar are enemies now.
看看我的科妮莉娅
One only has to look at Cornelia.
她像只可怜的伤心的小鸡，被人拔了毛，煮了
Poor sad chicken, plucked and boiled.
也许格雷毕斯还会要我
Maybe Glabius will take me back.
我们好不容易把他甩掉了
we are well rid of him.
我们要给你找个比格雷毕斯的利用价值大得多的人
We're going to find you somebody much more worthwhile than Glabius.
我已经在全城人面前够丢脸，蒙羞的了
I've been dishonored and shamed before the whole city!
胡说！
Nonsense!
一个上等家庭出生的女孩子的好名声
A girl from a good family can never be dishonored
决不会被一个像庞贝那样的险恶的下等人所玷污
by a villainous little pleb like Pompey!
决不…
No...
整件事在别人眼里看起来像个傻子一样的人，是我！
it is I who has been made to look foolish.
丢脸的人是我！  我想让他死
It is I who have lost face!  I want him dead.
我想他死
I want him dead.
你的心愿一定会实现的
And that you shall have.
庞贝要为此付出代价
Pompey will eat sand for this.
翻译:TLF字幕组